what's the best way to stay healthy in
the face of so much conflicting
nutrition information
well ideally you would go to the source
the gold standard the peer-reviewed
medical literature and read through the
stacks of the latest medical journals
but who's got time for that I do welcome
to the nutrition facts podcast I'm your
host Dr Michael Greger if you had a
plant-based diet you may wonder do we
really need to take supplements like
vitamin B12 let's find out
um hello from Jonathan how do you
recommend navigating supplements
multivitamins protein barriers I'm not
sure what to trust give me the LAX
regulation absolutely well certainly
there's this regulation is indeed lacks
um so what protein powder to get no
protein powder why would anyone need
protein powder to get protein same way
you get carbs same way you get fat from
a Whole Foods ideally hold plant foods
and no reason to take a multivitamin
um there are some things that people may
need in some supplement form for example
vitamin D for getting interact with
sunshine vitamin B12 you're not eating
vitamin B12 45 Foods
um so how do you get supplements that
aren't like contaminated with something
or actually have what they say they have
um probably the best way to do it is to
get one that is USP certified so that's
a third-party certification entity that
makes sure that whatever says on the
label is what is actually in the bottle
doesn't mean it's good for you or
anything I mean they you could have USB
certification of snake oil but at least
it would be actual snake oil at the dose
that they say on the package so it's
kind of truth in advertising okay this
is from Heidi new to plant-based mostly
fruit diet okay for anything vitamin B12
supplement absolutely or evine B12
fortified Foods one of those two
um critically important for anyone
eating a plant-centered diet even if
you're not
um even if it's not strictly plant-based
um critically important to do okay
Gabrielle or Gabriel
um what what can cause tingling
cessation in a whole food plant-based
diet besides B12 deficiency I presume
you mean tingling sensation kind of uh
fingers and toes that's a sign of a
peripheral typically it's not a
peripheral neuropathy
um why so if let's say you have a
problem with your nerves why would it
show up as tingling in your fingers and
toes well those are the longest nerves
in your body
um so the the the nerve in your toe
actually goes all the way up to your
spinal cord from your toe all the way up
to spinal cord one nerve like one long
skinny teeny little string of spaghetti
but like almost microscopic actually
microscopic all the way up isn't that
amazing one you know you think of cells
as being microscopic this uh this cell
is like you know three feet long
um so you can imagine if there's any
problems with your nerves those are the
nerves that are going to really show it
first right these ones that are so long
and vulnerable and so you get this kind
of uh
um that typical thing but it can be
caused all sorts of things there's all
sorts of toxins uh medications
um that can do it and so you just really
need to go to a neurologist and they go
through the differential diagnosis all
the various things that can cause it
um there are other nutrition
deficiencies that can do it
um and you just some heavy metal
toxicities can do it
um all of theirs start immune diseases
all sorts of things so you just got to
get checked out we got mechanical
do you have short-term effects with
inspection B12 levels
um uh so I presume clinical effects do
you actually feel differently
um in the short term from inspection B12
you may not which makes it so Insidious
but you can start showing these Club
subclinical
um uh um issues in terms of rising home
assisting or something which you
wouldn't really feel but may have
negative consequences so
um so a regular reliable source of
vitamin B12 is critically important and
uh so for those eating plant-based diets
for example I would recommend either
sufficient vitamin B12 45 Foods or
taking one 2 000 microgram
um uh B12 tablet once a week get all the
B12 you need uh super cheap safe easy
convenient
um and critically important can you
synthesize enough vitamin D during the
warm months to last you throughout
winter yes in terms of enough vitamin D
to live
um I mean that's the whole point is that
during this uh some months you know you
had high latitudes you build up enough
and it's stored in your fat and you kind
of live through the winter and then you
get more
um the next year but do you have enough
in your body for Optimal Health
that we don't know the answer and we
suspect that it's probably you probably
dip too low and indeed you see that uh
you know the that study the Oxford
um uh study on uh vegans in the UK High
latitude vitamin D perfect in the summer
dips
um too low during the winter months
um and uh so uh it's probably good when
you're getting into finished sunshine to
supplement your diet with vitamin D and
I would recommend like a 2000
international units of vitamin D3 a day
for anyone getting insufficient sun
doesn't matter where you live even in
the warmer months if you're inside all
day doesn't matter how much sun there is
outside you're not gonna make enough
because it actually it relies on
cutaneous exposure without sunblock
without clothes what do we have next
this is from Stephanie I don't know if
vitamin D3 is okay for a whole food
plant-based because I've read very due
to his vegan rather than vitamin D3 okay
there are vegan sources of both vitamin
D2 which is Source predominantly from
um fungi from mushrooms
um and vitamin D3 which is sourced
predominantly from sheep's wool bud is
also from lichen which is the
kind of an uh algae based multicellular
organism but uh but not an animal
um uh so uh so yeah you can get vegan
vitamin D3
um
all d2 is vegan but the D3 is probably
preferable just because the studies
showing increased longevity with vitamin
D supplementation we're all done on
vitamin D3
um and so since that's what the studies
were done on we don't know if that
necessarily translates to uh D2 so I
would just use D3 if you have a choice
if it's important for you to be vegan
you can get a vegan D3 no prop
we would love it if you could share with
us your stories about Reinventing Your
Health through evidence-based nutrition
go to nutritionfacts.org testimonials we
may be able to share it on our social
media to help Inspire others to see any
graphs charts Graphics images or studies
mentioned here please go to the
nutrition facts podcast landing page
there you'll find all the detailed
information you need plus links to all
the sources we cite for each of these
topics for our Vital timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics you can
order the ebook audiobook or hard copy
of my latest book how to survive a
pandemic
for recipes check out my new how not to
diet cookbook it's beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes for delicious
and nutritious meals and of course all
the proceeds are received from the sales
of all my books go to charity
nutritionfacts.org is a non-profit
science-based Public Service where you
can sign up for free daily updates on
the latest in nutrition research via
bite-sized videos and articles
everything on the website is free
there's no ads no corporate sponsorship
no Kickbacks it's strictly
non-commercial not selling anything I
just put it up as a public service as a
labor of love as a tribute to my
grandmother whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition